またそんな顔して 唇噛み締めて
mata sonna kao wo shite
There you go, making that face again,
biting onto your lips.
kuchibiru kamishimete
弱さを隠してるけど
yowasa wo kakushiteru kedo
You're hiding your weak side,
その瞳の奥 うずくまる君が
sono hitomi no oku
but deep in those eyes,
uzukumaru kimi ga
I can see you cowering.
本当の心なら
honto no kokoro nara
If you had a true heart,
思って 泣いて 一人で 不安で
omotte, naite, hito yonde, fuwande
you would care, cry, call for someone and worry.
なんで 痛いの 持ってんだ
nande itai no mottenda
Why are you holding onto the pain?
僕に そっと 預けてよ
boku ni sotto azukete yo
Share some of it with me.
直ぐじゃ無理と思うのならば
sugu ja muri to omou no naraba
If you don't think it's possible right away,
少しずつでいい
sukoshi zutsu de ii
you can do it slowly, bit by bit.
翼の無い僕等はきっと
tsubasa no nai bokura kitto
We don't have wings,
tobenai toki mitsuketeru dake
but I'm sure we're only finding times that we can't fly.
飛べないと 決め付けてるだけ
koe no kagiri kimi wo yobu yo
I'll call for you to the limits of my voice
声の限り君を呼ぶよ 迷わないように
mayowanai you ni
so that you won't get lost.
フワリ心舞い上がれ あの風に乗せて
fuwari kokoro maiagare
Soar up to the sky with your gentle heart,
ano kaze ni nosete issei erose
ride on that wind, and get it all at once.
Natsume
Yuujinchou
夏目 ちょい待ち
Hold on a minute, Natsume.
Could you write your name on this?
これに名前書いてれよ
名前？
My name?
旧校舎で何かやるのか
Are you going to do something at the closed-down school building?
肝試しよ
We're doing a courage test.
笹田
Sasada.
If we don't gather a certain number of people, we can't get permission.
ある程度の人数を集めないと使用許可がおりないの
協力して
So, could you help us?
It sounds fun, doesn't it?
面白そうだろう 笹田の発案でさ
It was Sasada's idea.
よろしく
Thanks.
Ah, sure.
What?
何？
いや
Nothing.
意外だってさ
He's saying it's surprising.
Well, I didn't think our haughty class rep would be organizing a ghost hunt, either.
まあ 俺もまさかお高いクラス委員長がお化け大会を主催するなんて
なんかいった
Did you say something?
I'll call you when everything has gone through.
じゃ 決まったら連絡するから
Okay.
What is it?
何？
やっぱり見えないか
So they really can't see it?
や…やばい じゃな
D-Damn.
L-Later!
おい 夏目
Hey, Natsume!
何だあいつ 急に慌てて
Why's he in a rush so suddenly?
W-What was that, just now?
何 今の
The Dew God's Small Shrine
追いかけて来ないか
He's not chasing after me?
Natsume-sama!
夏目様
夏目レイコ様ですね
You're Natsume Reiko, aren't you?
違う レイコは祖母だ 彼女はもう亡くなっていて
No, Reiko is my grandmother.
She already passed aw—
Give me the Book of Friends!
友人帳を寄越せ 寄越さねばお前を食ってやる
If you don't, I'll gobble you up!
止めろ
Stop it.
ニャンコ先生
Nyanko-sensei...
Don't get in my way!
邪魔をするな
あれはお前のような低級の妖者が扱える代物ではない
That is not something to be used by a low-level Ayakashi like you.
黙れ
Silence!
それに 友人帳が私がそいつの死後もらい受ける約束になっておる
Also, I have a deal with him to receive the Book of Friends once he dies.
In other words, it's already been promised to me.
つまり 先約済みだ
大人しく消えろ
So, be good and get lost.
お前こそ 消え失せるがいい
You...
should get lost!
Y-You're!
きさまは…
Get lost. You don't know who you're up against.
失せろ 身の程知らずな
That settles that.
よっこらせ
ありがとう 先生
Thanks, sensei.
では七辻屋の饅頭でいいぞ
You can thank me with Nanatsuji steamed buns.
So you took a liking to them.
気に入ったんだ
友人帳のことで俺を訪ねてくる妖怪には二種類いる
Due to the Book of Friends, there are two types of Youkai that come to me.
一つは今みたいに
The first type is like the one just now, those who are after the Book of Friends
名前が書かれた妖怪達を子分にしようと
友人帳を狙ってくる連中
in order to control the Youkai whose names are written in it.
そして もう一つが
And the other type is...
Excuse me.
御免下さいまし
友人帳の名前を返してもらえに来る連中
The ones who come back to have their names returned from the Book of Friends.
やーあの饅頭はいくつでも食えてしまうな
Ah, I could eat those steamed buns forever!
Oh, you returned another name?
何だ また名前を返してやったのか
Yeah...
まあな
Geez, what a waste.
まったく余計なことを
どんどん友人帳が薄くなってくではないか
The Book of Friends is getting thinner and thinner.
名前を返すと ひどく疲れる
When I return their names, I become very tired.
私がもらいうける頃には何匹残っているやら
I wonder how many will be left once I inherit it?
Maybe I should just eat this kid right now?
急ぐことこの時食ってしまおうかな
聞こえてるぞ インチキ招き猫
I can hear you, you damned, cheating fortune cat.
Thanks for the meal.
いただきます
はーい たくさん食べてね
Eat up, okay?
Okay.
はい
Touko-san is cheerful and kind.
塔子さんは明るくて優しい
滋さんは無口だけどいつも穏やかだ
Shigeru-san doesn't talk much, but he's always gentle.
この人達には絶対に迷惑をかけたくない
I don't ever want to cause these people trouble.
食べないわね
He's not eating.
猫ちゃん
The cat.
うわ 思い切り迷惑かけてる
I'm causing them utter trouble!
Maybe it doesn't like leftovers?
残り物じゃ駄目なのかしら
Maybe this will do the trick.
これならどうかな
お 食べた
Oh, it ate it.
Ah, you're right. It's quite the gourmand.
あら本当 グルメね
ったく
Geez...
あれ これ歯形か
Is that a tooth-mark?
Well, well. It has a special flavor.
いやいや なかなか美味ですな
どうしたの 貴志君
What's wrong, Takashi-kun?
あ いえ ちょっとむせちゃって
Ah, no, I kind of burned myself.
塔子さんたちに見えなくてよかった
I'm glad they can't see them.
Natsume-dono, I'd like you to return my name.
夏目殿 名前を返していただきたい
Sure thing.
あれ お前よく見れば露神のじじいじゃないか
Oh? Now that I've had a good look, aren't you the old Dew God?
え 知り合いなのか 先生
You know him?
Yeah. He's grown quite small, so I couldn't tell at first.
ああ ずいぶんちっこくなっていたから分からなかったが
Oh, that voice!
あ そうか お前は斑か
Ah, I know! You're Madara, aren't you?
なんだお前さん そのふざけたな
What's with your silly na—
Be quiet! I'll swallow you up!
やかましい 食うぞ
All right. Let's begin, then.
さて じゃ 始めようか
One who would protect me, show your name.
我を護りしものよ その名を示せ
So this is it.
これか？
Huh? It's stuck to the next one.
あれ これ次のと引っ付いてるぞ
You're right, they're completely stuck together.
本当だ ぴったりくっついておる
Looks like a grain of rice.
こりゃ米粒だな
米粒？
A grain of rice?
Reiko was a really sloppy gal.
レイコはズボラだったからな
She was probably playing with it while she was eating.
飯を食いながらいじったんだろう
Come on...
頼むよ
いた…たたた
無理に剥がすな 皮膚がびりびりする
Don't force it apart!
My skin feels all tingly!
I told you, didn't I, Natsume?
教えただろう 夏目
名前を破られれば身が裂ける
If their names get torn apart, so will their bodies.
燃やせば 灰になってしまう
If you burn it, they'll turn to ashes.
そうだった すまない 露神
That's right.
Sorry, Dew God.
へえ 驚いた
That scared me.
Well, that's how it is, so please give up.
まあ そんな訳だから 諦めてくれ
何？
What?
Takashi-kun! The bath is ready!
貴志君 お風呂どうぞ
Okay!
はーい
そんな薄情な…
How cruel!
Well, I can't return your name if I can't take them apart, can I?
だって剥がせないんじゃ
名前を返したくても返せないだろう
Please do something about it, Natsume-dono.
何とかしてくれ 夏目殿
Return my name! Please!
私の名前を返してくれ
無理なものは無理だって
You're asking the impossible.
夏目殿
Natsume-dono!
露神はこの先の七つ森に住んでおる
The Dew God lives in the Seven Forests, right ahead.
Well, I brought it because you told me to,
持って来いって言ってたから
持って来たけど こんなもの何に使うんだ
but what is it used for?
用心のためだ いいからしまっておけ
It's a precaution. Just put it away.
Oh, thank you.
あらあら ありがとう
あ いえ はい どうぞ
Ah, it's nothing.
Here you go.
ご親切にどうも
Thank you for your kindness.
傷んでいなければもらってくださいな
If it isn't bruised, please have it.
I can't eat it all by myself.
一人では食べ切れなくて
あ ありがとうございます いただきます
Thank you. I'll keep it, then.
いいお天気ですね
The weather is great, isn't it?
え あ そうですね
Ah, I guess.
それじゃ
Excuse me, then.
I wish I could say more thoughtful things at times like this.
こういう時もう少し気が利いた受け答えができればな
口下手なのが嫌になる
I hate being a poor speaker.
That old lady doesn't have much longer.
あの婆さん 長くないな
あまりうまそうな匂いじゃなかった
She didn't give off much of a delicious smell.
Don't be so rude.
失礼なこと言うなよ
This is the Dew God's place?
ここが 露神の…
何だ 変な顔して
What's with the weird face?
露神って 名前だけじゃなく本当の神様だったのか
The Dew God is a real god? And not just a name?
おお 来てくれたか 夏目殿
You came, Natsume-dono?
Damn, I was rude to him last night!
やば 昨夜の無礼三昧 祟られる
He'll curse me!
つーか レイコさんなんて罰当たりな
And Reiko-san, why'd you do something that'll get you cursed?
Oh? What's wrong?
おや どうしたのかな
He's in a panic because he believes you're a real god.
こやつ お前が本物の神様だったと慌てておるのだ
A-Ah, Dew God-sama!
え えーと 露神様
あはは 違う違う
No, no!
I'm called a god,
神と呼ばれているが
元はこの祠に住み着いた宿無しの妖ものだよ
but I'm just a wanderer that settled in this small shrine.
A long time ago, there was a long drought in this area.
その昔この辺りをひどい干ばつが襲ってな
惨状を憂えた若者がこの祠に祈った
Distressed by the disaster, the young villagers prayed at this small shrine.
And on the following day, it happened to rain.
そしたら来る日偶々雨が降った
以来村の者達はこの祠を露神と崇め
Ever since then, the villagers would worship the Dew God,
供物をどっさりと置いていくようになってな
and would leave many offerings.
気付くと 私は力に溢れ 姿も立派になっていたのだよ
And before I realized it, I was overflowing with power,
and my form became just as grand.
立派にね
Grand, huh?
The last time I met you, you were as tall as a human.
この前会った時は人間ぐらいあったぞ
Now I barely come up to their feet.
いまでは人の足も途絶えた
And just as my body grew because of people's faith in me,
だから信仰のおかげで大きくなった体も
I have diminished in size like this due to the lack of it.
こんなふうに縮んでしまったという訳さ
そうなんだ
I see.
ああ 桃 あげようか
Should I offer you a peach, then?
I already have a peach.
桃ならあるよ
ほら
Right here.
そうか あの人
I see, it was her.
You met Hana-san?
会ったのか 花さんに
ああ 花さんって言うんだ
Yeah.
So her name is Hana.
She is the sole person to come here and worship me now.
今やここに拝みに来てくれるたった一人の人間
へえ
I see. Together, huh?
なるほど 一緒にか
Yeah.
ああ 引っ付いているやつも一緒に名前を返れば
If I return the name stuck to yours, I won't have to force them apart.
無理やり剥がさなくても済むだろう
However, one problem came up.
ただ でかい問題が一つある
俺達はもう一枚の妖怪を知らない
We don't know the other Youkai.
In that case, I know him.
それなら 知ってるよ
本当か
Really?
レイコに負けた後私は悔しくてな
After losing to Reiko, I was really frustrated.
次に名前を奪われた妖ものがいると聞いて
After hearing that the next Ayakashi's name was taken,
I went to see him to gloat.
溜飲を下げるべくそいつの顔を見に行ったのだ
All right, it's done.
よし できたぞ
名は忘れたが こんなやつだ
I may have forgotten his name, but he was like this.
Is this really him?
本当にこいつなのか
Yes, it's drawn quite well if I say so myself.
ええ　我ながらよく画けておる
Did he have any hair?
毛はなかったの？
He... didn't have any.
毛は…なかったのう
Not even one strand?
一本も？
Not one strand.
一本もじゃ
He happens to live at Sannozuka.
当時そいつは三ノ塚に住んでおってな
陰の虫で 陰を沿って移動
He's also the god of shadows and moves by walking among them.
What? What is it?
何だ どうした
H-Hey! Why are you laughing?
こら 何を笑っておる
Are you making fun of my drawing?
私の絵をばかにするのか
San
ええい この罰当たりども
You damned, accursed fools!
San
And so, our Youkai search began at Sannozuka.
三ノ塚で妖怪探しが始まった
しかし 数日を費やして探したものの
But after spending several days searching for him,
we were unable to find him.
やはり見つけることはできなかった
San
Hey, you look sleepy.
何だ 眠そうだな 捜索疲れか
Tired from all the searching?
まあね
Yeah.
That's right, Hana-san can't see him.
そうか 花さんには見えないんだ
Even though he's within breath's reach.
息がかかるほど近くにいるのに
Oh!
あら
どうも
Hello.
あなたもお参り？
Did you come to pray too?
あ まあ
Ah, yeah.
よかったわ
That's great.
It seemed like I was the only one coming recently.
もう最近来るのは私だけみたいで
露神様お寂しいんじゃないかと思っていたんですよ
I was thinking that the Dew God was lonely.
いつ頃からお参りに
When did you start worshipping him?
Ever since I was a kid.
小さい頃からよ
へえ
Promise you won't laugh, okay?
笑わないでくださいね
私一度だけ露神様お見掛けしたある気がするんです
I think that I saw the Dew God once.
女学校からの帰り道
I was on my way back from girls' school.
その日も今日みたいな天気で
The weather was just like today's, too.
I came to pray just as I always do, and when I raised my face,
いつものようにお参りをして
顔を上げたら
I saw a leg behind the shrine.
祠の後ろに足が見えたんです
I was surprised, but I pretended not to notice.
驚いたけど気付かないふりをしましてね
I then saw a person wearing an old man's mask, who was in quite a good mood.
そうしたら 翁の面を被った人が気持ちよさそうに
"The weather is great today," he said.
今日はいい天気だなって
私 思わずそうですねって言ってしまいそうになったけれど
I almost replied without thinking, "Yes, you're right."
人間に姿を見られたと知ったら
But I felt that if a human saw him, the Dew God would disappear.
露神様が消えてしまう気がして
でも今でも思うんですよ
But even now, I think to myself that it would've been better if I had replied.
思い切って声をかけたらよかったかしらって
だって露神様はいつも一人ぼっちでしょう
The Dew God is always alone, right?
I don't think I'd be able to handle being alone.
私なら寂しくて耐えられないかも
So, I thought I should at least talk to him.
だから せめて声を…
いつも一人ぼっちでしょう
He's always alone, right?
Alone...
一人 一人は寂しい
Being alone is lonely.
Being alone is painful.
一人は苦しい
Being alone...
一人は…苦しい…
is painful...
苦しい
It's painful...
重い
It's heavy...
Don't sleepwalk!
寝惚けるな
You had a nightmare last night, didn't you?
お前 昨夜魘されておったな
You were heavy!
先生が重かったんだよ
You had an opening in your mind.
心に隙があったのさ
Weak minds invite spirits.
弱い心は魔物を呼ぶ
If you don't want to lose your life,
命を落としたくなかったら
you should never let your guard down.
どんな時でも気を緩めないことだ
ま もっとも私は早く命を落としてもらったほうが
Well, if you lose your life quickly,
友人帳も早く手に入って嬉しいがな
I'll be able to get my hands on the Book of Friends fast and be happy.
The next time you sleepwalk, I'll pull out the fur on your tail.
今度寝惚けたら
しっぽの毛抜くからな
You're a demon.
鬼だな
I don't want to be told that by a Youkai.
妖怪に言われたくない
I found him, Natsume-dono!
見つけたぞ 夏目殿
Are you sure?
間違いないんだな
Yeah, he really was on this mountain.
ああ やっぱりあいつはこの山にいった
I called for him, but he ran away.
声をかけたら 逃げてしまったが
He couldn't have gone too far, though.
まだそう遠くへは行っていまい
Sensei, let's split up!
先生 二手に分かれるか
Hold up.
来た
どうした
What's wrong?
Something bad is coming.
なんかやばいのか来る
Something bad?
やばいの？
I have come.
参りました
That was him!
こやつだ むこうから現れおったわ
He appeared from over there!
He looks nothing like your picture!
絵と全然似てないじゃないか
Don't be stupid, it was the spitting image of him!
ばか言い そっくりじゃないか
The only thing that's the same is the character!
同じなのは字だけだ
Natsume, use the mirror.
夏目 鏡だ
Reflect the sunlight and blind him!
日の光を反射させて目暈しにするのだ
I see!
そうか
Sensei!
先生
I have come.
参りました
Nasume-dono!
夏目殿
I have come.
参りました
I have come to get food.
食べ物をいただきに参りました
I have come.
参りました
ね 私と勝負しない
Hey.
How about fighting me?
If you beat me, I'll give you food.
私に勝ったら 食べ物をあげる
Or you could eat me.
なんなら あたしを食べてもいいわよ
I'm Reiko.
あたしはレイコ あなたの名前は？
What's your name?
I got it!
分かった こいつの名前は…
His name is...
I have come.
参りました
Natsume!
夏目
Susugi, Dew God, I return your names!
濯 露神 名を返そう
Are you listening, Dew God?
聞いてるの 露神
I am Reiko.
聞いてるよ レイコ
They won't always be bringing offerings, you know.
いつまでも供物は続かないわよ
現に今日だって桃一つないじゃない
You didn't even get one peach today.
Ah, you're right.
ああ そうだね
People are cruel and only care for themselves.
人はとても現金で薄情よ
You should find a better home while you have power.
力があるうちに
もっといい住処を探すのが身のためね
Thank you, Reiko.
ありがとう レイコ
But once you are loved,
けれど一度愛されてしまえば 愛してしまえば
and once you have loved, you cannot forget it.
もう忘れることなどできないんだよ
Natsume!
夏目
Is it okay for you to walk now?
もう歩いて大丈夫なのか
あのう 濯って妖怪は陰を使って村へ降りて
That Susugi Youkai would walk along the shadows to go to the village,
[Note: "Susugi" - to wash.]
and in exchange for receiving food scraps, he would wash that house's dishes.
残飯をもらう代わりに その家の皿を洗って返るんだってね
Oh, so you looked it up.
何だ 調べたのか
These days, the city is bright even during the night,
今じゃ町は夜でも明るいし
so we might not see him anymore.
もう会うこともないかもな
He has friends on the mountain.
山には仲間もいる
I'm sure he's glad to have cut his ties with humans.
人間なんかと縁が切れてあいつもせいせいしてるさ
You think?
そうかな だったらいいけど
I hope that's true, then.
I brought you some peaches, Dew God.
露神 桃 持って来てやったぞ
Dew God?
露神
I'm here, Natsume-dono.
ここだ 夏目殿
あれ また小さくなったな
You got smaller again.
Yeah.
まあな
あ 光出したぞ どうしたんだ
You're glowing? What's wrong?
Well, Hana-san has left.
ああ 花さんが行ってしまったんだ
Hana-san had been sick for a long time,
花さんは長いこと患っていてな
and it took everything she had to come here recently.
最近はここへ来るのもやっとだったんだ
She was the last human to have worshipped me.
花さんは私を信仰をしてくれた最後の人間
So, once she dies, I will disappear.
彼女かいけば 私も消えるのさ
I'll... I'll worship you!
俺が…俺が信仰するよ
Even if it's impossible, I'll come pray every day!
毎日は無理でも 拝みに来るよ
You can't.
駄目だよ 夏目殿 君は私の友人だ
You are my friend, Natsume-dono.
This is fine.
これでいいんだ 花さんと一緒に行ける
I can go with Hana-san.
I've always...
ずっと ずっと見ているばかりだったか
I've always done nothing but watch her.
But now...
これで 人に
Now, I feel like I'll be able to touch her.
あの人にやっと触れることができるような気がするよ
She heard you.
聞こえてたんだよ 花さんには
She heard your voice, Dew God.
あんたの声が 露神
Thank you, Natsume-dono.
ありがとう 夏目殿
Humans have been such charming creatures in the past, and even now.
昔も今も
人間とは可愛いものだな
The weather is great today.
今日はいい天気だな
そうですね
Yes, you're right.
ん？ どうした 夏目
What's wrong, Natsume?
Hey, what are you doing?! What a waste!
こら 何をする もったいない
Don't say things that'll get you cursed.
罰当たりなことを言うな
There's nothing here!
ここには何もおらんぞ
今日はいなくっても 明日はいるかもしれない
Not today, but there may be something tomorrow.
What's important is a caring heart.
思う心が大事なんだよ
あ 何やってんたよ このまぬけ猫
What are you doing, you stupid cat?
That's "fortune cat" to you, you idiot!
招き猫じゃ ばかもの
Meow!
ニャン
何がニャンだ 饅頭返せ
What do you mean "Meow"?
Give me back the steamed buns!
Hey!
こら
ニャン
Hold it, you steamed bun thief!
待て 饅頭泥棒
They're mine!
私の饅頭だ
I'm the one that bought them!
買ったのは俺だろうが
待て こら
Hey, hold it!
No way!
やーだぴー
ニャンニャンニャン
色づく 西空に
hi no tsukurishi zora ni
On that day where the sky was ablaze,
差し込む一筋の陽
sashikomu hitosuji no hi
and rays of light were piercing through,
夕立の雨上がりに
yuudachi no ameagari ni
the evening rain had stopped,
気付く夏の匂い
kizuku natsu no nioi
I noticed the scent of summer,
ひしめく光が照らす
hishimeku hikari ga terasu
and the crowded, shining lights.
想いに耳を澄ませば
omoi ni mimi wo sumaseba
If I turned my ear to my thoughts,
聴こえし友の面影
kikoeshi tomo no omokage
I could hear traces of my dear friends.
夏夕空 薫り立つ
natsu yuuzora kawarirazu
The summer evening sky
鮮やかな過ぎ去りし日々
azayaka na sugisarishi hibi
and the vivid passing days were just the same,
心のまま笑いあった
kokoro no mama warai atta
and so I laughed; it was just like
あの夏の思い出よ
ano natsu no omoide yo
my memory of that summer.
Next Time on
Natsume Yuujinchou
The Mysterious Person at the Eight Fields
おい 夏目
Hey, Natsume.
八ツ原の妖ものが人間にやられたと泣いておるぞ
The Ayakashi from the Eight Fields are crying because some human got them.
妖怪が見えるやつの仕業ってことか
Which means someone who can see Youkai did it?
He seems kind of suspicious.
あいつ どえらく怪しい
君は？
Who are you?
I'm Tanuma Kaname.
俺は田沼要